In the 5th century AD, the Roman Empire
confronted a new enemy from beyond the
great plains of the steppe. Renowned for
their skill as horsemen, these were the
Huns who quickly proved themselves to be
some of the fiercest opponents Rome
fought in late antiquity, taking on the
professional Imperial army from the
Balkans to the Rhine frontier and
sacking several of the Empire's cities.
What was it, however, that made the Huns
seemingly stand out [music] from the
many other enemies the Romans faced at
the time?
For context, we should briefly mention
what the interactions between the Romans
and the Huns were. The Huns first came
to the notice of the Romans during the
late 4th century AD, driving several
other tribes before them into retreat,
such as the Goths. The Huns' exact
origins remain unclear to this day, but
they may have been connected to the
ancient Xiongnu who once fought against
Han China before they began migrating
westward across the steppe. The Huns
quickly established themselves as fierce
warriors and conquered a large empire
stretching across much of the steppe and
Europe. During the 440s AD, they
campaigned extensively against the
Eastern Roman Empire under their leader
Attila and raided the frontier along the
Danube, sacking several cities and
killing and enslaving many people.
Attila seemed poised to threaten the
Imperial capital of Constantinople as
well, and thus the Romans agreed to pay
him large subsidies to avoid more costly
confrontations. The relationship between
the Huns and the Western Roman Empire,
by contrast, was more friendly at first.
The Roman commander Flavius Aetius even
made extensive use of Hunnic warriors as
allies in his campaigns. However, in 451
AD, Attila nevertheless invaded Gaul,
coming into contact not just with the
Romans, but also the Germanic kingdoms
that had been established there during
the 5th century. As Roman power waned,
the Huns caused widespread devastation.
However, they were eventually defeated
at the Battle of the Catalaunian Fields
by Aetius, who was supported by many
barbarian allies. Very soon, however,
Attila had managed to regroup and
invaded the West once more in 452 AD,
this time targeting the empire's
heartland of Italy. Although the Huns
once more caused much chaos, such as
when they stormed the fortress city of
Aquileia, the campaign ultimately ground
to a halt and the Huns withdrew, likely
due to supply shortages and outbreaks of
plague among Attila's army. Attila's
death a few years later then led to the
collapse of [music] Hunnic power as his
successors failed to keep their subject
peoples in check. That the Huns were
formidable enemies of the Romans is,
however, not in doubt. But was there
anything new about them that made them a
greater threat, or had the Romans'
ability to respond to such dangers
simply changed? Hunnic warfare. The Huns
were famed for their skill as cavalry,
specifically for fighting as mounted
archers. They made use of sophisticated
composite bows to strike at enemies from
a distance and with impressive stopping
power, while making use of their high
mobility to keep their enemies away from
close quarters until they were
sufficiently weakened by volleys of
arrows. Once this was achieved, the Huns
could come in to close quarters and
finish off their opponents, making use
of a range of melee weapons and lassos.
However, it is worth remembering that
although the Huns' horse archers were,
by far, their most famed troops, as
their empire expanded, they also began
to incorporate troops from their
numerous subject people into their army.
Thus, the Hunnic armies faced by Rome
would come to also include large numbers
of infantry, as well as other types of
cavalry. While provenly formidable, we
should note that there does not seem to
have been anything radically new in
Hunnic tactics that caught the Romans by
surprise. The Huns may have been more
aggressive than other nomadic armies,
but otherwise did not stand out in a
tactical [music] sense from other Roman
enemies who used similar troop types.
Rome had also been fighting armies that
included horse archers both as a
supporting role and the mainstay of
their forces for centuries. And while
there had been some heavy defeats
suffered at the hands of these types of
armies, the Romans, in fact, had a long
history of success in fighting horse
archers, such as the campaigns of
Ventidius against the Parthians in 39
and 38 BC, the Mithridatic War against
the Sarmatians in 69 AD, or the Battle
of Satala against the Persians in 298
AD. Instead of fighting in any kind of
new way, it was instead their aggressive
and brutal character that made the Huns
stand out to the Romans from other
barbarians. There was, however, one
aspect of Hunnic warfare that made them
a greater threat than other nomadic and
tribal armies: their ability in siege
warfare. Unlike the Sarmatians, for
instance, who could raid Roman provinces
but never seriously threaten
well-fortified settlements and forts,
the Huns were able to successfully lay
siege to Roman strongholds such as
Raetiaria and Aquileia, making use of
scaling ladders, battering rams, and
siege towers. Unfortunately, we don't
know how they came to possess such
knowledge, made more unclear by the fact
that the subject people of the Huns,
like the Germans, also lacked great
ability in sieges during this time. Some
more likely scenarios are that the Huns
could have learned the art of siege
warfare from warriors who previously
served in the Roman army or via Roman
deserters. In sum, the tactics and
equipment used by the Huns explains some
of their success, but were not the
deciding [music] factor. A key advantage
compared to other tribal and nomadic
forces [music] was the Huns' unusual
ability in sieges, which allowed them to
directly threaten Roman cities and
forts. But to more fully answer this
question, we must, therefore, look
inward to the Roman Empire and army
during late antiquity to determine if
changes within them affected the Huns'
successes. The Rome of late antiquity.
The Roman military of the 4th and 5th
[music] centuries was different in many
ways from its more famous counterparts
during the Principate. Yet, there
remained many similarities as well. The
troops were now split into two main
branches, each with its own command
structure. [music] The first were the
Limitanei, who were mostly based close
to the Empire's frontiers. The second
were the Comitatenses, who were
generally based further inland and
undertook most major field operations.
The Comitatenses have sometimes
mistakenly been described as the
successors of the famous Roman legions.
However, in truth, both they and the
Limitanei contained legions, as well as
many other units of infantry and
cavalry. The Romans fought as a combined
arms army with many different types of
troops, with most infantry and cavalry
being well-armored and armed units
intended mainly for close quarters. They
were supported by numerous troops armed
with missile weapons, especially archers
with composite bows. And the army during
this period also contained a higher
number of specialist cavalry, such as
the heavily armored cataphracts. Using
this flexible combination of troop
types, [music] the Romans had been
highly successful against armies similar
to the Huns in the past. And during late
antiquity, still won most battles they
fought. Much has been made by
commentators in the past of the Roman
military's employment of foreign
recruits, which were accused of
barbarizing the army with unreliable
soldiers. However, treachery from these
barbarians were extremely rare, and they
otherwise performed just as well and
loyally as any other Roman soldier.
While recruits born within the empire
continued to make up the great majority
of the regular army. It was only the
Western Romans in their empire's final
years who started to more heavily rely
on barbarian contingents, generally
known as foederati, to supplement Roman
regulars. But this was the exception
rather than the norm during this period.
Although the Romans were still
undeniably a great power, the Huns also
fought them at a time when the empire
was in decline and distracted by
internal political squabbling. In fact,
it was only on a few rare occasions that
the Huns encountered strong Roman
resistance and were otherwise able to
raid their territory with relative ease.
During this period, Roman commanders
were generally much more cautious about
fighting large-scale battles since they
could not afford the potential loss of
prestige and influence that a costly
defeat entailed. Civil wars and power
struggles were also alarmingly common in
this period, especially in the Western
Empire. Indeed, the reasoning behind the
new organization of the Roman military
was likely not so much to better fight
against foreign enemies, but rather to
try and disperse the empire's military
strength enough to deter potential
usurpers against the emperor, who also
kept troops [music] close to the
imperial capitals under their own
command or a close subordinate [music]
with which they could more quickly
responds to Roman rivals, just as they
could to foreign threats. Thus, the
Romans could not respond as effectively
to the Huns as they had to other enemies
in the past on [music] account of their
military and the trust and political
will of its leadership having been
weakened over centuries of infighting.
Hunnic strength or Roman weaknesses. The
Huns were ferocious and skilled warriors
whose talent as horse archers made them
both valued allies and formidable
enemies alike. This, as well as their
greater skill at siege warfare compared
to other barbarian armies, made them
stand out from other Roman enemies, and
we should not wholly discount their
martial abilities as a reason behind
their early successes. The Huns' brutal
character and raids also made an
impression on the Romans, seemingly
setting them apart from other tribal
armies in how much more ruthless they
could be. The historian Callinicus, for
example, had this to say of their
attacks on the Eastern Roman Empire. The
barbarian nation of the Huns became so
great that more than 100 cities were
captured and Constantinople [music]
almost came into danger, and there were
so many murders and so much bloodshed
that the dead could not be counted. They
even captured the churches and
monasteries and slaughtered great
numbers of monks and nuns. However, we
should also remember that aside from
this ability in sieges, there was
nothing novel or unexpected in the way
the Huns fought compared to other armies
the Romans had faced coming from the
steppe, whom they had defeated on many
occasions. Nor were the Huns invincible,
as they suffered setbacks of their own
against the Romans, [music] who were
able to mount strong resistance even
with the other problems they were
facing. Therefore, to conclude, the
successes of the Huns were in large part
thanks to weakness within the Roman
Empire caused by Roman infighting,
rather than the Huns themselves, despite
their fierce reputation.
If you'd like to help us keep creating
and get early access to our videos,
behind-the-scenes content, and other
perks, consider becoming a member right
here on YouTube or joining us on
Patreon. Every bit of support helps.
>> [music]
>> And as always, thank you so much for
watching.